<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: review | Udooz!]]></title>
  <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-23T14:27:12+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[M Sheik Uduman Ali]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Python for Data Analysis by Wes &#8211; O&#8217;Reilly]]></title>
    <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/12/book-review-python-for-data-analysis-wes-oreilly/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/12/book-review-python-for-data-analysis-wes-oreilly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/12/rc_cat.gif" rel="prettyPhoto[551]"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-552" title="rc_cat" src="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/12/rc_cat.gif" alt="" width="180" height="236" /></a></p>

<p>Python getting become the heart of data analysis works.  You can see variety of books taught machine learning, data analysis and big data processing based on Python.  To get into that world, this book is the basic to learn Python ecosystem for data analysis.</p>

<p>Pandas is one of the notable data analysis library along with the famous NumPy and SciPy libraries.  Wes McKinney who has implemented Pandas has written this book.</p>

<p>As a primer for data analysis, this book has been well written.  With the enough sample data for learning purpose, Wes explains NumPy, Pandas and matplotlib libraries in addition to the knowledge required on file handling, data loading, storage, wrangling and aggregation.</p>

<p>Wes spent a worthy spaces for IPython &#8211; an elegant command line IDE for Python data analysis.</p>

<p>As a basic learning book, notable effort taken for the sample data like MovieLens, US Baby Names, USD food database.  These helps the reader to understand those libraries practically.</p>

<p>Sometime you may get a feel of 470 pages is a very detail oriented for just learning Python libraries.  It is up to your comfort level to make short cut.</p>

<p><strong>Python for Data Analysis would be your first and good stepping stone</strong> for to work on &#8220;Data Analysis or Machine Learning&#8221; field.  This book is worth buy.</p>

<p>For book details: <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023784.do" target="_blank"><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023784.do">http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023784.do</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Cloud Architecture Patterns by Bill Wilder &#8211; O&#8217;Reilly]]></title>
    <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/11/book-review-cloud-architecture-patterns/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/11/book-review-cloud-architecture-patterns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/11/cat.gif" rel="prettyPhoto[526]"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-527" title="cat" src="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/11/cat.gif" alt="" width="180" height="236" /></a></p>

<p>Bill Wilder who is a MVP in Windows Azure has taken nice initiative in the cloud computing space with cloud architecture patterns.  Good collections.</p>

<p>Cloud computing relatively new and evolving technology, where we are facing so many recurred problems when dealing with application migration.  Bill introduces the basic tenants of cloud computing and design principles as Cloud Computing architecture patterns in this book.  There are 14 basic and common cloud computing patterns in this book.</p>

<p>The whole chapter 1 discusses on Scalability in depth.  I really liked his explanation on Performance vs Scalability.  Also, he listed out the characteristics of Cloud-Native applications.</p>

<p>Though it is not well fit into &#8216;pattern&#8217;, Horizontally Scaling Compute pattern discusses all design and anti-design aspects.  The Queue-centric workflow discusses the loosely coupled aspects.  It covers the asynchronous programming characteristics of cloud-native applications.  However, asynchronous and end user responsiveness related problems not covered in this, or as a different pattern.</p>

<p>He well touched the CAP theorem, sharding, fan-out quite well.  The multitenancy pattern can be explained much more better way.</p>

<p>The colocate and valet key patterns are nicely covered efficient use of network and trust with third party service integration.</p>

<p>The patterns try at best to vendor-neutral.  Fortunately, it lights up more on Windows Azure.</p>

<p>This book is very useful for people who are new to cloud computing space and going to construct/migrate application on this.</p>

<p>For well experts and people who have already spend their life on cloud computing, would be a refresher.</p>

<p>Well attempt for basic cloud computing architecture concepts.</p>

<p>You can buy this book at <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023777.do" target="_blank"><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023777.do">http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920023777.do</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review: Windows PowerShell for Developers by Douglas Finke, O&#8217;Reilly]]></title>
    <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/10/book-review-windows-powershell/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/10/book-review-windows-powershell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/10/cat.gif" rel="prettyPhoto[512]"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-513" title="cat" src="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/10/cat.gif" alt="" width="180" height="236" /></a></p>

<p>Douglas Finke is an MVP for Windows PowerShell.  This one point is enough to say the quality of this book.</p>

<p>When I was started learning and writing Powershell scripts, I really got crazy about that.  It has elegant syntax which will impress both developers and administrators.  Powershell is not just for Administrator.  This book is for developer.  The first 10 chapters cover the following different aspects:</p>

<ul>
<li>Quick introduction</li>
<li>text template transformation</li>
<li>Powershell in UI</li>
<li>Domain specific language using PS</li>
<li>Net.Webclient and Powershell</li>
</ul>


<p>The Chapter 11 covers Powershell 3.0.</p>

<p>The content is concise and clear.  Every chapters taking you in different level.</p>

<p>For beginners, &#8220;Getting Started&#8221; and &#8220;The Dime Tour&#8221; covers PowerShell basics.  This will give you different introduction to the developers, but not at the basic level.</p>

<p>Otherwise, every chapters will impress you like writing &#8220;Ruby&#8221; script in Linux world. <img src="http://udooz.net/blog/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif" alt=":)" class="wp-smiley" /></p>

<p>If you are a .NET developers, then this would also be in your book shelve in near feature.</p>

<p>Purchase this book at <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920024491.do" target="_blank"><a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920024491.do">http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920024491.do</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Review &#8211; Code Simplicity, Max, O&#8217;Reilly]]></title>
    <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/06/developer-review-code-simplicity-max-oreilly/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/06/developer-review-code-simplicity-max-oreilly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/images/2012/05/s.gif" rel="prettyPhoto[467]"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-468" title="s" src="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/05/s.gif" alt="" width="145" height="190" /></a></p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>One more theory book on software design and this book explains the simplicity of code.  This book has written by Max who is the Chief Architect of Bugzilla project.  This is a 90 page book with putting some effort on software design, changes to a program, defects and testing.  Howerver, first three chapters make me boring. </p>

<h2>In Detail</h2>

<p>I really got bored with first three chapters, probably I might not be right reader for that part.  Chapter 4 starts with some good coverage on how to justify and value your current design targeted to implement a feature.  Chapter 5 Changes explains three flaws in changes of software code which is the excellent part of this book.  The three flaws have been explained with examples which is normally missed in software theory books.</p>

<p>Chapter 6 DRY is very common, thankfully author took only 3 pages.  Remaining chapters are covered various best practices on Simplicity, avoiding complexity.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I have enjoyed chapter 5, partially chapter 4.  Apart from these all the other are common aspects.</p>

<p>You can buy this book at <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920022251.do">http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920022251.do</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Review &#8211; Machine Learning, Drew &#038; John, O&#8217;Reilly]]></title>
    <link href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/05/review-machine-learning-book-oreilly/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://udooz.github.io//blog/2012/05/review-machine-learning-book-oreilly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/04/cat.gif" rel="prettyPhoto[421]"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-422" title="cat" src="http://udooz.github.io//blog/images/2012/04/cat.gif" alt="" width="180" height="236" /></a></p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>It is very interesting to read a hard core computing book from authors those are not in the computing industry.  Their area of studies really make them as right choice for writing this book.  Drew Conway studies international relations, conflicts and terrorism using tools of mathematics, statistics and computer science.  John Myles White in &#8220;how humans make decisions&#8221;.  Obviously, both are Ph.D students.</p>

<p>Machine learning is one of the grooming area in the computing world which is actually a branch of artificial intelligence.  Based on the given data, we can capture characteristics of interest of our unknown underlying probability distribution.  This book thoroughly covers  various disciplines such as classification, ranking, regression, regularization, optimization, etc  with practical examples using &#8220;R&#8221; language.</p>

<h2>In Detail</h2>

<p>If you are a programmer, you may little bit astonished first time to use R.  Later, you will understand that &#8220;R&#8221; is not the language of programming, but excellent companion for people in statistical field.  So, you may not fully comfortable with &#8220;R&#8221; after reading the first chapter &#8220;Using R&#8221;.  Authors also mentioned that &#8220;R remains a relatively niche language, even among experienced programmers&#8221;.  However, It would be good if they explain R syntax and its usage crisp and short in the Appendix section.</p>

<p>The chapter 1 (Using R) and 2 (Data Exploration) make you start the journey slowly with many good theories on data analysis.  The visual explanation of &#8220;data as rectangle&#8221;, MxN matrix of data into single row or single column view are good learning.  Inferring data is another good point.   Wherever required,visual representations come for you to understand.  Otherwise, they comfortably explains the concepts textually.  Agile people should be patience on this.</p>

<p>&#8220;Chapter 3Classification : Spam filtering&#8221; make your journey at the highest speed, with lot of interesting turns.  After two chapters with academical effect, this chapter make you feel like reading fictions. They starts with an example of how can you predict a person is man or woman based on the weight and height.  They called this mechanism as &#8220;separating hyperplane&#8221; and also explained a way of taking decision called &#8220;kernel trick&#8221;.</p>

<div>
  <div>
    &#8220;Chapter 4 Ranking: Priority Inbox&#8221; is another chart buster which provides you some good knowledge on &#8220;sorting with unknown ordering&#8221;.  GMail&#8217;s priority inbox and Amazon&#8217;s book recommendation are few examples.
  </div>
  
  <div>
  </div>
  
  <div>
    &#8220;Chapter 5 Regression: Predicting Page Views&#8221; thoroughly explained the regression concepts and linear regression.  He frightened us with an example of smoking habits and their longevity. <img src="http://udooz.net/blog/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif" alt=":)" class="wp-smiley" />
  </div>
</div>




<div>
</div>




<div>
  The remaining chapters gives you the same good experience on concepts like Regularization, Optimization.  Chapter 8 takes you another level and teaches you unsupervised learning.
</div>




<div>
</div>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<div>
  When you have enough time on the week-end and want to learn truly some interesting and futuristic concepts in computing.  Do read this book followed by working out the examples.  If you are serious developers and coding is your passion, then this book will take you to some level up and incite your innovative ideas for your products.  For academic people, this should be one of the paper in your course.  A very good book from O&#8217;Reilly  by actual field experienced authors.  You can buy this book at <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920018483.do" target="_blank">http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920018483.do</a> or <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-Hackers-Drew-Conway/dp/1449303714" target="_blank">http://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-Hackers-Drew-Conway/dp/1449303714</a>.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
